<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A chorologicall discourse of the vvell ordering, disposing, and gouerning of an honorable estate or reuennue Briefely describing the duties of diuers officers therein to be imployed: for the better preseruing, improuing and augmenting of the same. Together with certaine briefe and necessary tables for the valuation of leases, annuities, and purchases, either in present or in reuersion. Written by T. C. Gent.</title>
            <title>Chorologicall discourse of the well ordering, disposing, and gouerning of an honourable estate or reuennue</title>
            <author>Clay, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5371.9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898985</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150825</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73749)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150825)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1983:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A chorologicall discourse of the vvell ordering, disposing, and gouerning of an honorable estate or reuennue Briefely describing the duties of diuers officers therein to be imployed: for the better preseruing, improuing and augmenting of the same. Together with certaine briefe and necessary tables for the valuation of leases, annuities, and purchases, either in present or in reuersion. Written by T. C. Gent.</title>
                  <title>Chorologicall discourse of the well ordering, disposing, and gouerning of an honourable estate or reuennue</title>
                  <author>Clay, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 57+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by George Eld dwlling [sic] in Little-Britaine,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another issue of STC 5371.5 with a cancel title page. The subsidiary title page for the tables on E1r in this and STC 5371.7 retains its date of 1618--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the St. John's College Library, Cambridge University, Cambridge, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Interest --  Tables --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Administration of estates --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Estates (Law) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150825:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A <hi>CHOROLOGICALL</hi> DISCOVRSE OF THE WELL Ordering, diſpoſing, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of an Honorable Eſtate or Reuennue.</p>
            <p>BRIEFELY DESCRIBING the duties of diuers Officers therein to be imployed: for the better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing, improuing and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting of the ſame.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH CERTAINE BRIEFE AND NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Tables for the valuation of Leaſes, Annuities, and purchaſes, either in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or in reuerſion.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>T. C.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Aeſtas quamprimum fuerit componite nidos.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by GEORGE ELD dwlling in Little-Britaine. 1621.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150825:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:150825:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150825:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO ALL THE RIGHT Honorable, Noble, and Worſhipfull Lords, Owners, Poſſeſſors, and Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of Reuennue, to whoſe view and vſe this preſent Treatiſe ſhall come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE, and RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T being manifeſt, the two maine materials out of which Honor and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie are created, to be Vertue and Reuennue: as the firſt being conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to be noted in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of men, both milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie and ciuill, is of all to be imbraced: ſo the latter ſeruing to ſuſtaine Honor, and being as it were the very nerues and ſinewes thereof, is of none to be neglected. Reuennue therefore, and the due ordering thereof to the beſt aduantage, and leaſt charges
<pb facs="tcp:150825:4"/> of the Lords and Owners of the ſame, is the ſubiect which in this enſuing Diſcourſe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of: which although in ſome particular Offices, others haue heeretofore more largely handled, yet in this briefe and generall kinde no man to my knowledge hath hitherto labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. That I haue endeauoured to be briefe, is becauſe I would not be tedious to ſuch whoſe weightie affaires otherwiſe abridge them of time for theſe matters. Yet I preſume (for the moſt part) this breuitie is without obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and being ſufficient for the purpoſe it intendeth, <hi>fruſtra fit per plura, quod fieri poteſt per pauciora.</hi> Such as it is, I humbly preſent it as the beſt meanes I haue, to teſtifie the great deſire in me to doe ſeruice to the Nobilitie of my country, whoſe fauourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of theſe my poore endeauors I only craue and entreate, and ſo reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors and Worſhips euer deuoted. THO: CLAY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:150825:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CARMEN AD Auctorem, ſeu Paſſus ad Athenas.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TAm bene, tam graphica deſcribis ſingula penna,</l>
               <l>Diſponens docta, munia cuique manu:</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t facile conſtet cuiuis tentare volenti</l>
               <l>Commoda de ſtudijs multa ſcatere tuis.</l>
               <l>Ingenij ſpecimen das non vulgare ſagacis,</l>
               <l>Et lumen genij non mediocre boni.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſta legat Quaeſtor, ſtudeat Geometricus iſta:</l>
               <l>Officij partes noſcet vterque ſui.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: Widmerpoole.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:150825:5"/>
            <head>IN DVE COMMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DATION OF THE Author, his Worke and worth.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>REuennues Order, Officers, and Lawes,</l>
               <l>VVith each mans dutie how eſtates to raiſe:</l>
               <l>Of euery loſſe and profit the true cauſe;</l>
               <l>Thou here deſcrib'ſt, in plaine yet pleaſant phraſe.</l>
               <l>Thy precepts briefe, yet pithy in each part,</l>
               <l>Declares thy iudgement, and extoll thine Art.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In purchaſe, ſale, exchange, or leaſing out,</l>
               <l>(Be it in preſent or reuerſion)</l>
               <l>This little Tract ſo cleareth euery doubt,</l>
               <l>As ſhewes it ſelfe in ſuch commerſion,</l>
               <l>For Lords and Owners all, a worke ſo rare,</l>
               <l>That none yet extant can with it compare.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>ADAM SMITH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150825:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A CHOROLOGICALL Diſcourſe of the well ordering, diſpoſing and gouerning of an Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate or Reuennue, wherein is briefly deſcribed the duties of diuers Officers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be imployed, for the better preſeruing, improuing, and augmenting of the ſame.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1. Of the definition of an Honorable eſtate, and of the Officers and Miniſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the ſame in generall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or that, according to the precept of the graue and learned Romane Orator <hi>Cicero,</hi> the inſtitution of all things whereof any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is to be made, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued, ought to take his beginning at Definition: it ſhal not be amiſſe, but very neceſſary, firſt to define what this Honorable eſtate or Reuennue wherof we purpoſe to entreat
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150825:6"/> is, and then orderly to proceede to the particular precepts and obſeruations to be handled in the ordering of the ſame.</p>
               <p>As touching the definition therfore: I call that an honorable eſtate or Reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, where any Lord or owner thereof is by the bleſſing and prouidence of God, either by inheritance, guift, purchaſe, or otherwiſe, endowed with Honors, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Lordſhips, Houſes, Lands, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſuch like poſſeſſions as haue belonging vnto them Royalties, ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, franchizes, liberties, and other priuiledges, and immunities, not inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to common eſtates, and tenures. For although that honorable titles (in reſpect of mens perſons) doe properly belong vnto none but ſuch who by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, office, place, the Princes free guift, or ſuch like, may iuſtly challenge the ſame, yet euen men of meaner ranke may be ſeized of ſuch honorable eſtates. And for as much as diuers Lords and owners of ſuch eſtates now a dayes (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through negligence, ignorance, feare of too much expence, or the like,
<pb facs="tcp:150825:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> I know not) for want of skilfull, diſcreet and faithfull Officers and Miniſters to that purpoſe, doe not only daily loſe diuers of their Royalties, ſeruices, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, and caſuall profits, to the ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; diſmembring of their Mannors, but alſo ſuffer many encrochments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealements, and other nuſances, to be oftentimes made and committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them to their great, and ſomtimes irrecouerable preiudice: which contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe by the care and prouidence of skilfull, diſcreete, and honeſt Officers would quickly be found out and preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: My purpoſe is therefore heere to deſcribe ſuch an order in the manna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, diſpoſing and gouerning of ſuch eſtates, as whoſoeuer ſhall be pleaſed (after mature conſideration) but to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſame, I doubt not but he ſhall finde great profit and contentment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and the courſe nothing ſo chargable to be maintained as many men may imagine, being that the ſurpluſſage of of the profits ariſing by the well mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of ſuch an eſtate, ſhall yearely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150825:7"/> vnto a greater matter then the ſurpluſſage of the charge which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would come vnto.</p>
               <p>To proceed therfore, I ſay, that to the well managing of an Honorable eſtate, there is required Officers and Miniſters skilfull, diſcreete, faithfull, and honeſt. And now we are to enquire what and how many they be; what is each mans particular duty, and how to make choiſe of them.</p>
               <p>Officers of Reuennue belonging to the well mannaging and gouernment of an Honorable eſtate, may generally be diuided into Officers of order, and Officers of charge.</p>
               <p>Officers of order are the Auditor, Surueyor, learned Steward, &amp; Solicitor, which I ſo terme, aſwell for that they ſerue to direct the whole buſines of the Officers of charge, by enforming each man of the particular duties belonging to his place, and by ſeeing that the ſame be duly performed: as alſo, for that they themſelues (in reſpect of their proper offices) are not chargeable with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt
<pb facs="tcp:150825:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> of any profits, nor accomptable for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Officers of charge are all ſuch which haue ſome charge or other impoſed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, as the receiuing and disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Lord his monies, the collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his rents, fines, and caſuall profits, the ouerſeeing of his Demeſnes, cattell, and husbandry, the cuſtodie and ſale of his woods, the prouiſion of his houſe, or any other ſuch imployment for which they ſtand accomptable. And theſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers are twofold, <hi>viz.</hi> of Receipt and of Expence.</p>
               <p>Officers of Receipt are the Receiuers generall and particular, the Storer, Woodward, Bayliffs, Collectors, and ſuch other Miniſters, which haue the charge and receipt of the Lord his Rents and other profits of his Reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue: and theſe are all accomptable to the Auditor for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Officers of Expence are the Steward of the houſe, and vnder him all other Officers of the houſhold, which haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny charge impoſed vpon them, whereof
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150825:8"/> they ſtand accomptable to him, as the Gentleman of the horſe, Clerke of the Kitchin, Baker, Brewer, Butler, and ſuch like, all which for breuities ſake I omit, purpoſing in this diſcourſe to entreate of none but ſuch as are chiefly neceſſary for the managing of Land-Reuennue, and which haue ſome charge impoſed vpon them for which they ſtand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptable to the Auditor.</p>
               <p>And now that we haue ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed what Officers are of neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit to the well ordring &amp; mannaging of an honorable eſtate, we will accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our former propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded method, ſet downe the particular dutie of each ſeuerall Officer as they fall out in order and dependance, reſeruing the Auditor for the laſt place, becauſe in his office, as in a maine ſtreame or Riuer, the effects of all the other, as the branches therof, doe concurre and are made manifeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. Of the Office, dutie, &amp; choyſe of a Surueyor.</head>
               <p>THe Surueyor is an Officer of order, &amp; one of the principall in an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150825:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> Reuennue; whoſe Office is to view and ſuruey all and ſingular the Honors, Mannors, Lordſhips, lands and Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Lord, and to ſearch out all the profits, Royalties, priuiledges, and cuſtomes thereunto belonging, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſame orderly in his Bookes of Suruey; and alſo to ſet downe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh in his ſaid Bookes, the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar lands of euery Tenant within each Mannor, truly butting &amp; bounding each ſeuerall parcell thereof, and expreſſing the auncient names of the ſame, the qualitie, quantitie, and yearely value of each mans Tenement, the tenure by which he holdeth, and the Rents and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices yearly due and payable therefore, with the Feaſts and dayes of payment, entering each tenure orderly and ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally by it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>To take notice of ſuch encrochments concealements, purpreſtures, and ſuch like, as he ſhall meete withall in his view and perambulation, and to certifie the Lord or his Commiſſioners therof, that the ſame may be reformed, or preſented
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150825:9"/> to the Iurie at the next Court, and aren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lord his profit, as alſo to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of Rents decayed, and to doe his beſt endeauour to reuiue the ſame.</p>
               <p>To make good &amp; formall Terrars or Rent-rolls out of his Bookes of Suruey, expreſſing therein orderly all rents, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, and certaine profits, within each Mannor, and the times that they are due, payable, and to be performed; and to deliuer the ſame to the Bayliffs wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may gather vp and collect the ſaid profits, and alſo ſee the ſeruices du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed to the Lord his vſe.</p>
               <p>To make out Suite-rolls contayning all the Tenants names that owe ſuite of Court to the Lord his Mannors, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing therein each ſeuerall tenure by it ſelfe, and what ſeruices and cuſtomes each Tenant holdeth by, as fealtie, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, reliefe, &amp;c. and to deliuer the ſame to the ſeuerall Stewards that they may thereby call the Tenants at the Lord his Courts, and be directed what to doe vpon euery change, as death, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enation, ſurrender, and ſuch like.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150825:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> And for the better performance of all theſe duties, and whatſoeuer els is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to be required at the hands of this Officer, he ought to be ſufficiently skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all the parts of Suruey, <hi>viz.</hi> the Mathematicall, Legall, and Iudiciall, which ſufficiencie to obtaine, he muſt be endued with theſe ſeuerall guifts or qualities following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he ought to haue the perfect vſe of ſome Mathematicall Inſtrument, as the plaine Table, Theodelite, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumferentor, or ſuch like, fitting for the vſe of Suruey; and alſo to be well ſeene in Arithmetick and the grounds of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ometrie: whereby he may be able aſwell to finde the errors which he may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in platting of grounds, or caſting vp the contents, and amend the ſame, as alſo to proue the truth of his worke and to giue a reaſon thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he ought to haue ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſonable knowledge in the common Lawes, eſpecially in ſuch generall points as are incident vnto, and doe moſt concerne a Mannor or Lordſhip:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150825:10"/> whereby he may be able to know and diſtinguiſh the ſeuerall tenures, rents, ſeruices, Royalties, and ſuch like prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall matters required in a Suruey: and to expreſſe the ſame orderly in his Bookes, Terrars, Rent-rolls, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he ought to be a reaſonable good Clerke, and to haue good skill in euidences of all ſorts, aſwell ancient as moderne; to be able to reade and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſame, whether they be in latine, French, Engliſh, or any other language heeretofore vſed in this land.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, he ought to haue good skill in the goodneſſe of grounds, and in the valuation of the profits &amp; commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities growing and ariſing out of the ſame, as Timber, vnderwoods, Mynes, Quarries, &amp;c. as alſo in the valuation of lands or caſual profits, to be leaſed, ſold, purchaſed, or exchanged, either preſent or in reuerſion, either in fee-ſimple, fee-Farme, vpon liues, or terme of yeares, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And now that we haue ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the office of a Surueyor, and how
<pb facs="tcp:150825:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> to make choyſe of him by the qualities he ought to be endued withall; we will proceede a little further, to ſhew the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and commodities that may and doe ariſe by this Officer executing his place honeſtly &amp; well: which although for the moſt part, they doe clearely ſhine and are manifeſt in that which we haue before ſpoken, yet becauſe this Officer of all others belonging to Reuennue, is hardly thought of, and moſt calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſuch as either vnderſtand not what vſe to make of him, or rather ſuch whoſe cloſe packing and ſecret iniuries are by him in danger to be laid open; it ſhall not be amiſſe to explaine the profit of his facultie a little better. Wherfore I haue heere laid downe the principall commodities of a good and abſolute Suruey, (ſo farre as at this preſent my memorie will ſerue me) in theſe ſix Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles following, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inprimis, it is a good meanes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the Rents and Cuſtomes of all natures from being concealed, left, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed: or their natures by euill diſpoſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150825:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150825:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:150825:12"/> Tenants or Officers any way altered or changed.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Item, to let, hinder, and auoyde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crochments that might be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Lord and Lord, Lord and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and Tenant and Tenant: or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing formerly made, to lay open and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer the ſame: as alſo in times to come to decide controuerſies that may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in this and diuers other caſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Item, in letting and ſetting of lands, in fineing of Coppy-holders, in ſale and exchange, a perfect Suruey is able to enforme the qualitie, quantitie, value, tenure, and ſcituation, aſwell and better then any other view that can be taken beſides. And by perfect Surueyes ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the Lord or his Commiſſioners ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting quietly at home, may not only themſelues aſſeſſe fines vpon the leaſes, &amp; cuſtomary eſtates, but alſo continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee both how themſelues and their Tenants be dealt withall by their Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards or other Officers put in truſt for the like matters.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Item, to reuiue decayed Rents,
<pb facs="tcp:150825:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Royalties, &amp;c. and to bring to light Concealements, forfeitures, and other ſuch like treſpaſſes and iniuries.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Item, a good Suruey is beneficiall to the Lord and his poſteritie, being as good euidence in lawe for any matter in controuerſie, as any other written In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument whatſoeuer of like antiquitie.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Item, the Plat well made is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to explane Euidences concerning the butting, bounding, and poſition, of any parcell that ſhall happen to be in controuerſie, eſpecially where the ſame controuerſie, or ſome principle therof, dependeth vpon the poſition; which cannot well be conceiued by euidences. And thus much may ſuffice for the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and dutie of a Surueyor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3. Of the learned Steward.</head>
               <p>THe learned Steward is alſo an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of order, and as needfull in an honorable eſtate or Reuennue as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatſoeuer, by whoſe care and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence chiefely the ancient rights, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150825:13"/> and cuſtomes of euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Mannor, Lordſhip, Bayliwicke, or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, are to be preſerued and kept, and the caſuall profits of the ſame yearely ſought out and manifeſted.</p>
               <p>He is by vertue of his Office, to keep duly the Leets and Courts within euery of the Lord his Mannors, at the times and places accuſtomed, aſwell for the good gouernment of the Lord his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in their due obedience towards him, as in the adminiſtration of equitie and iuſtice among themſelues, by inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all manner of offences, iniuries and treſpaſſes, that are enquirable or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable in the ſaid Courts; and ſuch as are there to be reformed by paines, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciaments, or ſuch like; to impoſe the ſame according to lawe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</p>
               <p>He is alſo to enquire of, enter, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreate out vnto the Bayliffe, all manner of caſuall profits happening and grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing due to the Lord of the Mannor by any forfeiture, concealement, eſcheate, ward, marriage, reliefe, herriot, waiue,
<pb facs="tcp:150825:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> eſtray, fellons and outlawes goods, new erections, purpreſtures, encrochments, Licences of all ſorts, as for digging clay, Chalke, Marle, &amp;c. for the paſſage of ſome water-courſe, for letting and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of cuſtomary lands for longer terme then the cuſtome will beare, &amp;c. as alſo by the common fine, head-ſiluer, green-hewe, or any other ſuch profit enquira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Court.</p>
               <p>To aſſeſſe and extract out reaſonably, and according to the cuſtome of the Mannor, the Fines of the cuſtomarie Tenants, vpon euery new admittance; by Surrender, death, or expiration of terme, and to enter orderly vpon the Roll all the ſeuerall Tenements, Cotta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and parcels of land contayned in euery ſuch admittance, with the ancient names, butts, and bounds of the ſame, and the yearely Rents and ſeruices due therefore: that ſo the diuers alterations which may happen by parcelling of lands and Tenements, may at all times plainely and euidently appeare without confuſion, which is a matter of great
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150825:14"/> moment and neceſſitie, though little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by moſt Stewards now a dayes, who for haſt, to cut their buſineſſe the ſhorter to their owne gaine, for the moſt part, neuer butt and bound the parcels granted, nor many times ſo much as name the ſame, or mention the Rents: whereupon it commeth to paſſe that in few yeares, not onely the Tenements &amp; lands are ſo mangled and diſmembred, as by the ancient Surueyes, Euidences, and Records, the ſame cannot poſſibly be ſet out vpon any occaſion offered: but alſo the cuſtomary is conuerted to free, and the Rents, Seruices, and caſuall profits thereof quite loſt and obſcured from the Lord, beſides the infinite troubles and ſuites that oft<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>times ariſe thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Tenants.</p>
               <p>To make out his Extracts of Court bipartite in Parchment indented, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the one part thereof, within one moneth next after euery Court to the Bayliffe, for him to collect the ſame, &amp; to ſend the other part to the Auditor at the time of the Audite, that ſo the Bayliffe
<pb facs="tcp:150825:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> may be duly charged therewith vpon his accompt: and alſo within the compaſſe of the yeare following, to engroſſe the the Court-Rolls, to remaine in the place accuſtomed, for the vſe and ſeruice of the Lord and his Tenants.</p>
               <p>Now concerning the guifts and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities wherewith this Officer is to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued for the better execution of his place, and by which he is to be made choiſe of for his ſufficiencie therein (ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie and diſcretion firſt and chiefly, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in him as in all other Officers of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uennue, being reſpected) he ought to haue good knowledge and experience in the common lawes of this land, thereby to be able readily to know and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of the authorities, priuiledges and iuriſdictions of ſuch Courts as are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and belonging to any Mannor, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, or Franchiſe, whether the ſame be Court-Leete, Court-Baron, Court of ancient Demeſne, Court of Pypowders, or the like; and to iudge and determine of the ſeuerall matters, actions, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which may happen, and are properly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150825:15"/> enquireable or determinable in euery of them. And to this end, it is good to make choiſe of ſuch a man as hath beene brought vp at ſome of the Innes of Court or Chauncerie, or hath practiſed as a Solicitor, Atorney or Councellor at lawe, whereby he hath gained good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</p>
               <p>He muſt alſo be a good Orator, to be able orderly, diſtinctly, and ſufficiently to deliuer a good and ſubſtantial charge to the Iurors, of ſuch matters as are to be enquired of and preſented before him, and to expound the lawe to them in caſes needfull.</p>
               <p>He ought moreouer, to be a good Clerke, to be able thereby to make good Court-Rolls, and to enter orderly in the ſame all matters preſented before him, as Eſſoynes, defaults of apparences both of free and cuſtomarie Tenants, deaths, alienations and deuiſes of freehold-lands, which are things very neceſſarie to be enquired of in a Court-Baron; (though for the moſt part now adayes neglected) for that when any Free-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150825:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> alieneth any parcell of his Freehold-land to a ſtranger, or by his will deuiſeth the ſame to diuers perſons, there the Lord hath an encreaſe of his Free Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and of their ſeruices, Wards, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefes, &amp; ſuch like; which are oftentimes quite loſt for want of ſuch preſentments: as alſo deaths, alienations, and ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Cuſtomarie Tenants, with En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crochments, Purpreſtures, Waiues, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayes, Reſcous, Pleas of Court, Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Treſpaſſes, and all other caſualties and profits preſented.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4. Of the Office and dutie of a Solicitor, and how to make choiſe of him.</head>
               <p>THe Solicitor is likewiſe an Officer of Order, whoſe Office chiefly (in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Reuennue, which onely in this place we purpoſe to entreate of) is to ſee that ſuch Priuiledges, Cuſtomes, Rents, Seruices, Debts, and profits to the Lord, which are to be reuiued, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed, or recouered by courſe of Lawe, and of which he ſhall be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150825:16"/> by the Surueyor, Auditor, Steward, or other Officer of authoritie, be duly and with beſt conuenience put in ſuite, and diligently and carefully followed to the beſt aduantage of the Lord.</p>
               <p>To ſee that ſuch Patents, Charters, Graunts, Feoffments, Deedes, Leaſes, &amp; other Euidences, wherby any Lands, Annuities, or other profits of Reuennue, are to be aſſured to the Lord, or wherby any ancient Priuiledges, Cuſtomes, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, or ſuch like, are to be reuiued and eſtabliſhed, be formally drawne and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed by skilfull Councell, to the intent the ſame may be good and effectuall in Law, to all ſuch intents and purpoſes as they ought to be made.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the principall matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Reuennue, which the Solicitor hath to looke vnto, and to be able to performe the ſame, he ought to be ſuch a one as hath beene trained vp to the profeſſion vnder ſome Councellor, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney, or other Officer belonging to the Lawes, or elſe ſome one which by following of diuers cauſes hath gained
<pb facs="tcp:150825:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> good experience, how to order his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires in euery ſeuerall Court both Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall and Temporall.</p>
               <p>He ought alſo to be a good Clerke, and to be able to reade and vnderſtand all ſorts of ancient Euidences, whereby he may the better declare vnto Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell the effect of his cauſes, and alſo be able to make out Breuiates of ſuch caſes as are in controuerſie, aſwell for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter information and memorie of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, as for helpe of the Iudges at the times of hearing.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, he ought to be conuerſant and well acquainted in all the Offices, where the Records of euery Court are kept, whereby to know where to ſearch for ſuch Records as ſhall be needfull in euery cauſe, and to know the Fees of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Officer and Miniſter in each Court vpon euery occaſion and buſineſſe that may happen, and thus much of theſe Officers of Order.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150825:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. 5. Of the Office of the Bayliffe, Collector, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THe Bayliffe is an Officer of Charge, belonging to ſome Mannor, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Franchize, or Libertie, whoſe Office principally is to collect and gather vp yearely at the Feaſts and times of Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due and accuſtomed, aſwell the Rents of the Freeholders, Coppyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Feefarmers, Leaſeholders, and Tenants at Will; as alſo the Fines, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciaments, paines and profits of Courts, Waiues, Eſtrayes, Fellons goods, Herriots, Reliefes, and all other caſuall profits happening within his Charge, and yearely at the Audit to accompt for the ſame.</p>
               <p>To take Diſtreſſes, to make Seizures and Re-entries to the Lords vſe, for non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment of Rent, or vpon other occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons when he ſhall be thereunto required by the Auditor, Steward, or other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of Authoritie.</p>
               <p>To ſummon the Lords Tenants that owe Suite and Seruice to his Courts, to appeare and giue their attendance at the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150825:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaid Courts, whenſoeuer they ſhall be appointed to be held, and to ſerue all manner of Precepts, Warrants, and Proceſſe graunted by the Steward in the Courts of the Mannor, or by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor on the behalfe of the Lord.</p>
               <p>And note, that in ſome Mannors the Office of the Bayliffe, as it is heere gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſet downe, is executed by two or three particular Officers beſides the Bayliffe, according to the cuſtome of the ſaid Mannor. For in ſome places there is one Officer which doth only collect the Rents of Aſſize of the Free and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomarie Tenants and no more, yearely making his Accompt to the Auditor for the ſame; and this Officer is in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces called a Reeue, and in ſome places a Graue, being alwayes one of the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie Tenants of the Mannor, an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Officer changing euery yeare, and bound to performe the Seruice by the tenure of his Land.</p>
               <p>Another ſerueth to collect the caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all profits yearely happening, as Fines, Amerciaments, Herriots, &amp;c. who alſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150825:18"/> is alwayes a Tenant of the Mannor, yearely choſen at the Court-Leete, or Court-Baron, according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Mannor.</p>
               <p>Theſe Officers ought to be honeſt and truſtie, of good diſcretion, abilitie, and conuerſation; and it is fitting that the Bayliffe (whether he be an Officer for life, or during pleaſure) ſhould put in good ſureties for anſwering the Lord his Rents and profits: for the other there needes no ſuch matter, for if they be delinquent it is a Forfeiture of their Cuſtomarie eſtates, which is Securitie good enough.</p>
               <p>As concerning other qualities, it were fitting they ſhould be able to write and reade, whereby to make perfect Notes and Bills to the Auditor of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of their Accompts, that ſo they may be the leſſe troubleſome to him in his Audits: and for all other matters they are to take direction, as occaſion ſhall ſerue, from the Steward, Auditor, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyor, or other Officer of Authoritie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150825:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. 6. Of the Office and dutie of the Woodward.</head>
               <p>THe Wood-ward is alſo an Officer of Charge, vnto whoſe care and truſt, the cuſtodie of the Lords Woods, and Receipt of the profits ariſing out of the ſame, are chiefly committed.</p>
               <p>He is therefore carefully to looke to the preſeruation of the Lords Woods, and vnder-Woods within his charge, &amp; to the well Fencing of ſuch of them as are incloſed, that the ſame be not ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or waſted, by breaking or putting in of hurtfull Cattell too ſoone after eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fall, before the young ſtuffe be growne paſt danger, or by cutting and hewing thereof at all times by lewd and diſordered people, which if they be not carefully looked vnto, are wont to ſteale Rods, Poles, Fewell, and ſuch like, out of mens grounds, and eſpecially the Lords Woods, vpon the waſts and elſewhere.</p>
               <p>To ſee that the Woodfalls be made at ſeaſonable times, for the more ſpeedy renuing and growing againe to the beſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150825:19"/> aduantage of the Lord, and at euery fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to haue ſpeciall care of the ſhred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and cutting of Tymber Trees, that in doing the ſame the bodyes be not ſpoyled and made to die, rot, or corrupt, by the euill and vnſeaſonable cutting of the Branches.</p>
               <p>To make Sale of the Tymber and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwood at ſuch times as are fitting, and when they ſhall be thereunto required, with good diſcretion, and to the Lords beſt aduantage, and to accompt yearely to the Auditor, not only for the felled Tymber and Vnderwood, but alſo for the tops of the Tymber Trees, for the blowne Wood, and for the Herbage, Agiſtament, Pannage, and all other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits made of the Lords Woods, and of the Soile of them.</p>
               <p>To ſee that ſuch Leaſees as doe hold any of the Lords Woods for tearme of yeares, doe not ſell or cut downe the ſame, but at ſeaſonable and conuenient times, neither that they cut downe and take away any more then is contayned in their Leaſes, and to ſee that they look
<pb facs="tcp:150825:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the Fencing and preſeruation of the young Spring after each fall, and doe in all things according as by their Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants they are bound to doe.</p>
               <p>To execute with good diſcretion, and to the Lords beſt aduantage, ſuch War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants as ſhall come vnto him from the Lord or his Commiſſioners, for Tymber for the repayring of Houſes, Bridges, Parke-pales, or ſuch like: and finally, to be carefull in the due execution of his place, in all other things that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now to be able to performe all theſe duties, he ought to haue good skill and iudgement in all theſe kindes of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, the want whereof is often the cauſe that ſome of them ſell ſuch good penyworths, as doe much enrich the buyer, and aſmuch endamage the Lord: He muſt therfore be able to giue a neere eſtimate in ſtanding Woods, what num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Cord wood, Billet, Fagots, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, one Acre with another doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; and likewiſe for Tumber-trees, to know what quantitie both of Tymber
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150825:20"/> and Fewell each Tree will make, that ſo he may apprize the ſame accordingly, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he may often be ouer-reached by a cunning Buyer.</p>
               <p>And for the better performance of his Office, it were very fitting that he ſhould haue very good knowledge in meaſuring of Tymber, both round and ſtanding, as alſo felled and ſquared; and aboue all, that he be very honeſt and conſcionable, to accompt truly for the profits of his place: And thus much may ſuffice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Officer.</p>
               <p>I might in this place bring in the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Warreners, Clerkes of Iron-workes, Lead-workes, Coale-mynes, Quarries, and ſuch other profits of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uennue accomptable to the Auditor; which I purpoſely omit, as well for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities ſake, as alſo for that nothing is or can be required either in the orderly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their places, or in the choiſe of them (skilfulnes only in the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie they are to deale withall excepted) more then <hi>Mutatis mutandis,</hi> hath beene ſhewed in the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150825:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. 7. Of the Office and dutie of the Storer.</head>
               <p>THe Storer is an Officer accomptable to the Auditor, who hath in Charge all ſuch Demeſnes of Paſture, Medow, Arrable, and other Lands, as are peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly in the Lords owne Occupation, with the Stocke thereupon employed: and his Office principally is to ſhew the profits that are made of the ſame, as of Corne, Cattell, Fell-wooll, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Commodities: which Officer in meane mens eſtates is termed the Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe of the Husbandry.</p>
               <p>This Officer is to ouerſee the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, that they doe their duties in the Manuring and Tilling of the Lords grounds, at fit and conuenient ſeaſons; to prouide of the beſt Corne for ſeede, and to ſee the ſame carefully and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably beſtowed, in ſuch grounds as are fitteſt therefore; to looke to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the Carts, Waines, Ploughs, and all ſuch other Inſtruments and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements of Husbandry, and to ſee the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150825:21"/> ſame repayred when they are out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; to ſee that the Husbandmen haue care, in the feeding and dreſſing of their Teemes &amp; working Cattell, &amp; to looke to the repayring and amending of the fences, hedges, &amp; ditches of the grounds in his charge, and all ſuch other matters belonging to Husbandrie.</p>
               <p>To ſee the Hay and Corne of all ſorts, renuing, growing, and encreaſing vpon the Lords grounds, carefully and ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably Inned: and after, at conuenient times Threſhed out, ſold and deliuered to the Lord his vſe, and to keepe true reckoning of the ſame from time to time, vntill he haue perfected his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt before the Auditor.</p>
               <p>To ſee that the Heards, Shepheards, and ſuch other Hindes, as haue the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodie of the Lords Cattell and flockes, do their true endeauours and duties in the feeding, curing, and preſeruation of the ſame, and to keepe true Accompt of them from time to time, aſwell of what commeth into the Stocke, as Cattell bred, bought, and receiued, <hi>(viz.</hi> Herri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots,
<pb facs="tcp:150825:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> Waiues, Eſtrayes, Felons goods, Preſents, and ſuch like) as of what go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of the ſame: as Cattell ſold, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to the vſe of the Lords houſe, or otherwiſe by Warrant; Cattell dead, loſt, ſtollen, or ſuch like; entreating the ſame orderly in a Booke, each vnder his proper title, that they may plainely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to the Auditor, vpon his Accompt without confuſion.</p>
               <p>To ſet downe in his ſaid Booke, the the true rates and priſes of all ſuch Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, as ſhall be bought or ſold by him, within the compaſſe or time of his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, with the times and places, when and where the ſame were bought and ſold, and the age and qualitie of the Cattell, as alſo to rate and apprize all ſuch Cattell, as he hath deliuered to the Lords vſe, or by his Commaund, at ſuch rates and prizes, as they were reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly worth in the Market at the time of their deliuerie: that ſo the yearely profit of the Lords Demeſnes, and grounds employed with Stocke, may the more plainely appeare vpon euery Accompt.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:150825:22"/>
               <p> This Officer, as concerning his quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ought to haue good skill in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Husbandry, and in Cattell, Corne, and Grayne of all ſorts; as alſo, to be perfect in buying and ſelling euery Commoditie belonging to his Charge, and carefull and honeſt in the execution of his place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8. Of Receiuers, both generall and particular.</head>
               <p>THe Receiuers generall &amp; particular, being likewiſe Officers of Charge, differ not much in the manner of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their places, neither indeede is there any neede of particular Receiuers but only in great Reuennues, where the Lords lands and profits lye diſperſed in many and farre diſtant places, and Countries: And therefore of them in generall.</p>
               <p>They are for the due execution of their Offices, to keepe their Receipts twice in the yeare, at times and places conuenient, and to giue warning and
<pb facs="tcp:150825:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> notice to the Bayliffs, Collectors, Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and other Miniſters, to bring in to thoſe places, the Lords Rents, and other profits due at thoſe times.</p>
               <p>To receiue and take Charge of the Lords monyes at the Audite and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, &amp; to ſee the ſame ſafely conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſuch places, where the Lord hath vſe thereof.</p>
               <p>To keepe perfect Abſtracts of all the Lords certaine Rents, eſpecially of the Farmers, and Leaſeholders, whereby they may call to ſuch Miniſters as are to pay them in, if they be ſlacke in their payments.</p>
               <p>To keepe alſo perfect Notes and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracts of all Rents reſolute, Annuities, Pentions, Stipends, Salaries, Fees, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and other certaine payments, yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by them payable, and iſſuing out of the Lords lands, by vertue of any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, Graunt, or other certaine aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in being, and out of controuerſie; and to make payment of the ſame, at the due and accuſtomed times, taking good and effectuall Acquittances &amp; diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150825:23"/> therefore, to the vſe, and on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Lord.</p>
               <p>To pay out vnto the Steward of the houſe-hold, and other Officers of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, as alſo to all Creditors, Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and others, to the Lords vſe, all ſuch ſummes of money as by the Lords Warrant, he ſhall be appointed to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, taking of them ſufficient Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances for diſcharge of the ſame, on the Lords behalfe.</p>
               <p>To keepe perfect and formall Bookes of all their doings for the Lord; both in Receipts, and Disburſments, and to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt for the ſame yearely to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the principall things belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Office of Receiuers, both generall and particular, which to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, there is no great skill or extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie ſufficiencie required, only they ought to be of abilitie, whereby to put in good ſecuritie for the due anſwering of the Lords moneyes, and profits, that ſhall come to their hands: alſo, they muſt be of good diſcretion in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:150825:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> of their buſineſſes and payments, that the Lord be not to ſeeke of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes, when any extraordinarie and ſodaine occaſion ſhall happen: and chiefly of all, they ought to be excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding honeſt and conſcionable, for that many ſummes of money, both come to their hands and goe out alſo, which the Auditor cannot charge them with, nor giue them allowance of, but vpon their owne voluntarie acknowledgement and confeſſion.</p>
               <p>And thus haue we briefly deſcribed the duties of all the moſt neceſſary Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Receipt belonging to an Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate: and now we will proceede to the Steward of the houſe, being the ſole Officer of expence accomptable to the Auditor, as concerning matter of Reuennue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9. Of the Office and dutie of the Steward of the Houſhold.</head>
               <p>THe Steward of the houſe, is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Officer of expence, in the due
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150825:24"/> execution of whoſe place many Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomicall precepts concerning the well ordering of an honorable Familie, might be conſidered, which heere according to my former propounded method, I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely omit; and will onely touch ſuch matters as doe moſt depend vpon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uennue, for which he is charged and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptable to the Auditor, which are the monyes to him deliuered by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers, and others, for the expence of the Lords Houſhold, as alſo the Beeues, Muttons, Corne, and graine of all ſorts, Wood, Coales, and all other prouiſions and Commodities receiued from the Storer, Woodward, Bayliffe, Warriner, or other Officer of Charge belonging to Reuennue, all which notwithſtanding they be deliuered to the peculiar Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of expence, to whoſe place they belong, yet the Steward is to haue the ouerſight of them, and to keepe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt both of their Receipt and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence.</p>
               <p>He is therfore to ſee to the deliuerie, and apprizing of all ſuch Commodities
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150825:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> and prouiſions as are deliuered in, from the Storer, Warriner, or other Officer, for expence of the Lords Houſhold; that the Rates be reaſonable, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Market at the time of their deliuerie.</p>
               <p>To call to Accompt weekely, or at the moſt monethly, all the inferior Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of expence: as the Gentleman of the Horſe, Clerke of the Kitchin, Keeper of the Granarie, Brewer, Baker, Butler, Pantler, and all others which haue any Charge of prouiſion to accompt for, and to ſee that euery of them do execute his place frugally and without waſte.</p>
               <p>To keepe faire and orderly Bookes, aſwell of the weekely or monethly Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts of all the foreſaid Officers, as alſo, of all other his owne Receipts and Disburſments, entering in the ſame each particular, in his due and conuenient place, and vnder his proper title, that all things may appeare without confuſion: &amp; finally, to accompt vnto the Auditor honeſtly and iuſtly at the end of euery yeare.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:150825:25"/>
               <p> Now concerning the qualities wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with this Officer is to be furniſhed, much might be ſaid, if I ſhould enter into Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomicall affaires, but to auoide tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and to wade no farther then my firſt intent, I ſay, that it is fitting this Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer ſhould be of honeſt life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, whereby to ſhew good example to others; of good abilitie &amp; reputation, whereby to curbe and keepe vnder ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne and diſordered ſpirits of inferior place and ranke; and alſo graue, wiſe and diſcreete, whereby to diſpoſe and order the buſineſſe committed to his Charge, and to gouerne the Lords Familie in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and laudable faſhion: And thus much may ſuffice concerning this Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer and all other of expence; from whom we will proceed to the Auditor our laſt, yet not leaſt Officer of Order.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. Of the Office and dutie of the Auditor.</head>
               <p>THe Auditor is an Officer of Order, and of all others belonging to Reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,
<pb facs="tcp:150825:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> one of the principall and moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie; for that by him the doings of all the former, are ouerlooked and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Lords profit: in which reſpect this Officer repreſenteth the Lord his owne perſon, and ought to haue more ſpeciall authoritie conferred vpon him then any of the former.</p>
               <p>He is by vertue of his Office yearely to take and examine the particular Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts of all and ſingular the Officers and Miniſters of Charge aforeſaid (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch as are accomptable to the Steward of the houſe) and to ſee that all manner of profits, wherewith any of them are to be charged, be duly and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly collected and anſwered.</p>
               <p>To enter duely in the Accompts ſo taken, all ſuch materiall changes and alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as may happen in the Rents, tenures, and Tenants names, either by Eſcheate, new Purchaſe, Sale, determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of eſtate, improuement, decay, or any the like accident, that the ſame may euidently appeare vpon euery oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion without confuſion.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:150825:26"/>
               <p> To ſee that the caſuall expences and Bills of Charges yearely brought in by the Bayliffe, and other Accomptants, to be allowed for Court Dinners, keeping of Strayes, repayring of the Pinfold, &amp; ſuch like, be reaſonable and fitting, and where they are exceſſiue, vnfitting, or vnneceſſary, to diminiſh or diſallow the ſame.</p>
               <p>Note, that in great eſtates, this &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſuch caſuall matters &amp; expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are left to the conſideration and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the Commiſſioners appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ordering of the Reuennue, &amp; there the Auditor of himſelfe hath not this power of allowing or diſallowing, but by conſent and approbation of the ſaid Commiſſioners, and by Bill ſigned with their hands.</p>
               <p>To make declaration of the ſaid Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts to the Lord, within ſhort ſpace after the taking of the ſame, and within the compaſſe of the yeare next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to engroſſe them faire and in good order, to remaine to the Lord and his poſteritie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150825:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> To take notice, and keepe true Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts of all Arrerages of Rents, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profits that may happen, and to charge the Accomptants with them from yeare to yeare, vntill they may be leuied &amp; anſwered: as alſo, to acquaint the Lord or his Solicitor with ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied Royalties, priuiledges, and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, as are fitting to be reuiued, or re-eſtabliſhed, and with ſuch arrerages of Rents and Debts as are to be recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Lawe, and to ſee that the ſame be put in Suite with the beſt conuenience whiles they are recouerable.</p>
               <p>To enroll faire and in a Booke made for the ſame purpoſe, all the Leaſes, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, &amp; other Graunts yearely made by the Lord or his Commiſſioners, thereby vpon any occaſion to be able to giue the Lord ſatisfaction, aſwell of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the thing leaſed or graunted, as of the end and determination of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now this Officer, in reſpect of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities he is to be endued withall, for the better and more ſufficient execution of his place, ought firſt and eſpecially, to be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150825:27"/> honeſt, free from corruption, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all his dealings.</p>
               <p>He muſt be trained vp in the facultie of an Auditor: whereby he may be able orderly to drawe downe out of the Bookes of Suruey, Rent-rols, and other the Lords Euidences, perfect viewes, and Accompts, as well Receiuers as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, of euery ſeuerall Lordſhip, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, Rectorie, Farme, Bayliwicke, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſuch like, duly diſtinguiſhed the Rents and profits yearely happening, &amp; the repriſes and deductions yearely go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, each vnder his proper title, and in his due place and forme.</p>
               <p>He ought alſo to be a good Clerke, to write a faire hand, and to haue the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ready vſe of his Counter, to be of good vnderſtanding, pregnant wit, and good apprehenſion, thereby the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to looke into the doings of ſuch Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptants, as he ſhall haue to deale withall, and to finde out the ſhifts, tricks, and deceipts, of ſuch as are euill diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and finally, he ought to be of good experience and ſufficient practiſe, in all
<pb facs="tcp:150825:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> matters concerning his facultie: which he being, and executing his place ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, and with iudgement, the profits that will ariſe to the Lord by this Officer are great, and more then ſodainely can be drawne to memorie: ſome of the principall whereof, notwithſtanding as a taſte of the reſt, I haue heere ſet downe in theſe Articles following.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Inprimis, an eſtate well ordered by a skilfull Auditor, giueth great eaſe and comfort to the Lord of the ſame, and helpeth to improue it ſelfe: for that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſmall profit is continually in the Lords eye; which in eſtates ill managed, (by men of no skill in Auditorie) are often, and for the moſt part, either quite concealed, or altogether neglected.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Item, a skilfull Auditor, in keeping due accompt of arrerages of Rents, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciaments, fines, and ſuch other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, is not only the meanes to make the Bayliffs, Collectors, and other Miniſters carefull to omit nothing of their duties, but alſo to keepe diſordred Tenants in the better obedience: for where there is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150825:28"/> no Auditor at all, or one that is remiſſe and of no skill, many caſuall profits, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially amerciaments are vtterly loſt, by the neglect of Miniſters, and for want of carefull looking vnto, which very thing is a great cauſe of diſorder among the worſt ſort of Tenants, animating them, aſwell to neglect their ſeruices &amp; duties to the Lord, as to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit iniuries &amp; treſpaſſes, one againſt another, by hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking, wood-ſtealing, breaking into Paſtures, and Corne, with their Cattell, and ſuch like: all which, if theſe amerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments were duly impoſed, leauied, and anſwered, would be more carefully loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto and auoyded.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Item, an Auditors accompt, is good Euidence to pleade in Court, for the holding or re-obtaining of any Rents, Royalties, Cuſtomes, Seruices, Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, Franchiſes, or ſuch like, formerly in poſſeſſion, and after loſt by neglect or otherwiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:150825:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. 11. The Concluſion, ſhewing the order how to gouerne an honorable eſtate, by the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers aforeſaid: and in ſmall eſtates, how to contract them to the Lords beſt aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</head>
               <p>HAuing before ſufficiently declared the ſeuerall duties of each particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Officer and Miniſter of Reuennue; together with the qualities euery of them ought to be endued withall, for the better and more effectuall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance and execution of their ſeuerall places, and Offices, it reſteth now only to ſhew and ſet downe, a little more plainely, the dependance that one Office hath of another, and thereby the order of gouerning an honorable eſtate by them, and how euery particular profit of Reuennue may be brought in charge, &amp; duly collected, and anſwered to the Lords beſt aduantage: wherein, for our better proceeding, we will comprehend al profits of Land-Reuennue, vnder theſe two generall heads, Certaine &amp; Caſuall.</p>
               <p>All Certaine profits of Land-Reuennue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150825:29"/> are enquirable by the Surueyor, and by him to be certified, and expreſſed in his Bookes of Suruey, as Rents of Free-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of cuſtomarie Tenants, of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes and Leaſe-lands, of Tenants at will, of herbage, and agiſtament, of Parkes, Woods, Foreſts, &amp;c. of Mills and Mulcture, of Mynes, Quarries, and ſuch like: of all manner of Royalties; as Fiſhing, Fowling, Hawking, Hunting, Free-warren, and ſuch other: Alſo, all manner of mouable Rents, as Hay, and Corne, Egges, Hens, Geeſe, and the like: And laſtly, all Rents of Scruices &amp; cuſtomes, being certaine, as for Licences of all ſorts, common Fine, releaſe of Suite of Court, head-ſiluer, green-hew, and ſuch other. Out of which ſaid Bookes of Suruey, being faire engroſſed &amp; made authenticall by Euidence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in certified, and the Iuries hands there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſubſcribed; a briefe Abſtract, and Suite-Roll, is to be made, and deliuered to the learned Steward, whereby he may not only call the Tenants to doe their Suite and Seruice at the Lords Courts,
<pb facs="tcp:150825:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> but alſo be directed by value of the lands how to aſſeſſe Fines vpon Coppyhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the like. Then alſo a perfect Rent roll is to be made out, &amp; deliuered vnto the Bayliffe, whereby he may col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and gather vp the ſaid certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, and accompt for them yearely to the Auditor, as before hath beene ſaid. Laſtly, the Bookes themſelues are to be deliuered vnto the Auditor, that out of them he may drawe downe, and make out the viewes of his Miniſters ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, and then to redeliuer them to the ſaid Surueyor, to remaine in his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodie for the vſe of the Lord or his Commiſſioners, in letting of Leaſes, and ſuch other occaſions.</p>
               <p>The Caſuall profits of Reuennue, are either enquirable by the learned Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in his Courts, or by the Auditor, at the time of his Audit.</p>
               <p>Caſuall profits, enquirable by the Steward, are Herriots, Reliefes, Wards and Mariages, Forfeitures, Waiues, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayes, Fellons and Outlawes goods, Fines vpon admittances of cuſtomary
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150825:30"/> Tenants, fines vpon Licences, purpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and new erections; amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and paines for default of ſuite of Court, mending, ſcowring, and clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Fences, Ditches, and Highwaies, Reſcous, Pound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>breach, and other like treſpaſſes, nuſances, and offences Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheats, Pleas, and Proceſſe of Courts, Fraies, bloudſheds, and the like; All theſe the Steward is to extract out, to the ſeuerall Bayliffes or other Miniſters, appointed to collect &amp; leauie the ſame, and to returne the duplicate of the ſaid Extracts to the Auditor, as before hath beene expreſſed. And it is fitting that ſuch of them, as are laid down in Court, the Receiuer or Bayliffe ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to take them vp to the Lords vſe, &amp; not to commit them to the Stewards charge, leaſt by that meanes he purſe the ſmall ones to his owne profit, and neuer accompt for the ſame, as fines of Licence of Brewing, digging of grauell, ſand, chalke, clay, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Caſuall profits enquirable, by the Auditor only, are profits of Faires,
<pb facs="tcp:150825:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> Markets, and ſuch like; wood-ſales, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtament and Pawnage; profits of the waſtes and Moores, as ſale of Heath, Turfes, Peate, Sand, Grauell, Marle, Chalke, Clay, and all other profits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſuall, and not elſewhere enquira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: In exacting of which accompts, the Auditor had neede be very circumſpect, and the Collectors, of the ſame very honeſt, for that commonly theſe are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes committed to the ſole truſt and diſpoſing of one man, both to ſell, and to accompt for the ſame, who if he be not honeſt and conſcionable, may year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defraude the Lord of a great part thereof; but the Auditor, if he be wiſe and circumſpect, may both finde out the falſhood, and take order to preuent the ſame.</p>
               <p>Theſe Rents and profits, both certaine and caſuall, being duly collected by the Officers and Miniſters thereunto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, ought at euery halfe years end, (or ſooner if occaſion require) to be paid vnto the Lords Receiuer, who vpon the receipt thereof, ought to giue his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150825:31"/> Acquittance to the Miniſter which pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, as for ſo much by him recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, of the iſſues and profits of his Office for that yeare: &amp; at the years end the ſaid Miniſter vpon the determination of his accompt, ſhall deliuer vnto the Auditor the ſaid Acquittance, whereby to charge the Receiuer with the monyes receiued, and ſhall for his owne diſcharge, take out a <hi>Quietus eſt</hi> for that yeares accompt vnder the Auditors hand.</p>
               <p>All the Miniſters thus hauing accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Auditot ſhall call the Receiuers, charging them, aſwell by their ſaid Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittances, as by the viewes, of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters accompts, their owne confeſſion, and ſuch other notes, as ſhall come to his hands for that yeare; and they for their diſcharge, ſhall produce the Lords Warrants, &amp; the Acquittances of ſuch perſons, to whom they haue paid any money; as alſo the bills of al charges and expences, by them that yeare disburſed, ſigned with the Lord or his Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners hands: all which, vpon the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of their accompts, they ſhall alſo
<pb facs="tcp:150825:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> leaue with the Auditor, aſwell for his warrantie of their ſaid accompts; as for the more effectuall charging of the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the houſe, and all other perſons, which are to accompt for monyes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſted by warrant or otherwiſe, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting likewiſe of a <hi>Quietus eſt</hi> vnder the Auditors hand for their owne diſcharge. And thus ſhall the ſaid Auditors pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, from accomptant to accomptant, as they depend one vpon another, vntill he haue finiſhed with them all: which being done, he ſhall make out his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the whole yeares buſineſſe, as before hath beene ſaid, bipartite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented, and declare the ſame before the Lord or his Commiſſioners, who ſhall ſigne the one part thereof, to remaine with the Auditor for his diſcharge; the other part thereof, the ſaid Auditor and Commiſſioners ſhall ſigne, to remaine to the vſe of the Lord.</p>
               <p>But heere me thinkes, I heare ſome obiect, that the ordering of an eſtate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner (being it requireth ſo many Officers) will be too chargeable
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150825:32"/> for moſt men, and therefore not to be put in execution, but only by ſuch as haue very great eſtates. To ſuch I thus anſwer.</p>
               <p>It is not ſo much the multiplicitie of Officers, that is required in the well ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of an eſtate, as the order and method to be vſed in the placing, and appointing of thoſe Officers: for there is no man of abilitie, but hath, and is at charge with ſo many as ſerueth his turne after his owne manner, which number would alſo (out of doubt) doe it in the forme heeretofore deſcribed, the Auditor only excepted, whoſe place the Lord himſelfe in ſmall eſtates, for the moſt part, executeth (and may well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the ſame if he haue leaſure, and be skilfull, but that few are, and thereby enſueth the moſt loſſe) therfore to come to the matter, and to ſhew how in ſmall eſtates, with ſeweſt number of Officers, and leaſt expence, an honorable Reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue may be well ordered, theſe two rules muſt be preciſely obſerued.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that none of the Officers of
<pb facs="tcp:150825:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> order be wanting (the Surueyor only excepted, who hauing once in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning perfected his Surueyes, there is ſmall vſe of him for many yeares after, ſo there be a skilfull Auditor, and a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Steward) and theſe Officers of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, neede be no great charge to any Lord, for that one man may ſerue to manage diuers Lords eſtates, hauing no further dependance vpon any of them, but only a reaſonable yearely Fee allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his paines, which if they be skilfull and honeſt, their diligence ſhall in ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſſage bring in, with aduantage, and eaſe the Lord of much labour and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe. And the more neerely to contract theſe Officers of order, one man may ſupply both the places of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Steward and Solicitor; and another, being capable thereof, may ſupply the places of Surueyor and Auditor: and of this Officer (the Auditor I meane) I would wiſh no Lord to be deſtitute, for where the Lord himſelfe taketh the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts of his Officers of charge, except he be very skilfull and painefull alſo,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150825:33"/> although his eſtate be but ſmall, yet for want of this Officer he may well loſe twice ſo much in the yeare (either by negligence and corruption of Miniſters, or by want of skill to examine their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) as would fee a good Auditor to doe the ſame: Yet let him alſo be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the choyſe of his Auditor, for many now a dayes take vpon them, both the name and place of Auditors, and yet are very ignorant in the due execution of that Office.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it muſt be duly obſerued, that no one man be put to execute Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of order, and Offices of charge both together, as Auditor and Receiuer, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor and Steward of the houſe, learned Steward and Receiuer, Bayliffe, Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or ſuch like: much leſſe that the managing of an eſtate, ſhould wholly, or for the moſt part, be committed to the charge of one particular man: for in both theſe caſes, it may eaſily be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, what great meanes &amp; ſtrong temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations they haue (if they be not of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding honeſtie and good conſcience)
<pb facs="tcp:150825:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſecretly to enrich themſelues, by the loſſe and hinderance of the Lord; or at the beſt, what danger of loſing many profits, by neglect, or for want of skill to preuent the ſame. And yet it is ſeene in moſt mens eſtates of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ranke, that one man hath the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all, both for order and charge; and he for the moſt part, of no further skill, then to ſet downe confuſedly his receipts, on the one part, and his disburſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on the other, &amp; ſo by comparing them to finde the difference: whereby alſo the Lord hath no other declaration of his doings, but the ſaid confuſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, in which all things for the moſt part come in in groſſe; and the profits of many Mannors, and disburſments of ſundry natures, are ſo mingled together, as they can neither for the preſent, nor in after-times, vpon any occaſion that may happen, be diſtinguiſhed, nor the Lord ſee whether he haue right or wrong.</p>
               <p>But to conclude, although it be not fitting, that one man ſhould execute
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150825:34"/> both Offices of order and of charge, nor that the whole ſhould be committed to one particular perſon: yet may theſe Offices of charge alſo in ſmall eſtates be conferred vpon a few perſons; for one man may be generall Receiuer, and Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the houſe; another may ſupply the places of Bayliffe, Wood-ward, Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and as many other Offices of charge as he is able to execute: and in this manner the Lord is in moſt poſſibilitie to haue all his profits truly anſwered, and narrowly looked vnto; where not only euery ſmall matter is taken notice of, by two or three ſeuerall Officers; but alſo euery Officer of charge, is to giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the profits he receiueth, and the Officers of order meddle no further, but to charge and diſcharge the moneys by the other receiued, to ſearch out the profits of Reuennue, and to ſee that each Officer of charge, doe execute his place with honeſtie and diligence.</p>
               <p>And thus haue I, in the beſt &amp; briefeſt manner I can, deſcribed the well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of an honorable Reuennue: wherin,
<pb facs="tcp:150825:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> in what I haue failed, I ſubmit my ſelfe to the reformation of the more iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: thus much by the way inferring, that I haue not in all points exactly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the order and courſe obſerued in the managing of the Royall eſtate of our Soueraigne; who beſides Land-Reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, hath many other, and great profits, yearely comming in by his Subiects, (not heere ſpoken of) the moſt of which are returnable into his Maieſties Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, where they are handled and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by thoſe great Maiſters of Arte and iudgement in theſe faculties, from whome I acknowledge to haue receiued that little skill and experience which I haue. What here is ſet downe, is drawne from them, and applyed to the vſe of the Subiects in their ſmaller Reuennues, which I leaue to the conſideration of all ſuch, whom it may concerne, and who haue hitherto loſt, by ill ordering of their Eſtates.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
